<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Addenda &amp; mvtanda, in the late defence of the marriage of an uncle with his niece being the daughter of the half-brother by the father's side / by the author of that defence.</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6190</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11965076</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11965076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51688</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51688)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 519:46)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Addenda &amp; mvtanda, in the late defence of the marriage of an uncle with his niece being the daughter of the half-brother by the father's side / by the author of that defence.</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27, 18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage law.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51688:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51688:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>ADDENDA &amp; M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TANDA,</hi> In the Late DEFENCE OF THE MARRIAGE OF AN UNCLE with his NIECE Being the Daughter of the Half-Brother BY THE FATHER's SIDE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Author of that Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1686.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51688:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51688:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Addenda &amp; Mutanda,</hi> In the late Defence of the Marriage OF AN UNCLE with his NIECE, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing the Daughter of the Half-Brother by the Father's Side.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 20. And they take no manner of notice under the ſecond of theſe Heads—of the Marriage of the Uncle with his Brother or Siſters Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.) This, I confeſs, is not very agreeable to what I have written in my <hi>Reſolution of Three Matrimonial Caſes,</hi> p. 3. Where, to prove that a Parity of Reaſon ought to be allowed in Matrimonial Prohibitions, I appeal to the Practice of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and I did it with reference to this very Caſe of an Uncle marrying his Niece, though it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51688:3"/> appears the <hi>Jews</hi> have no where forbidden it: And the Reaſon of the Miſtake was, That in general I remembred very well, that the <hi>Jews</hi> did prohibit ſeveral Degrees, which are not expreſly ſet down in the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and the Marriage of an Uncle with his Niece, ſeeming to me at that time, to have ſo exact a parity of Reaſon with that of an Aunt and her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, though now I am unalterably of another Opinion, and I preſume, I have ſhewn very good reaſon for it; I took it for granted, without conſulting the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Authorities which I there mention, and being in very great haſt, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by comparing the date of my Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with the time when thoſe Queſtions were propoſed to me, which will appear by the Preface to thoſe Caſes, that the Marriage of an Uncle with his Niece was forbidden by the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>P. 35. <hi>Fratres patrueles, conſobrini, ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tini,</hi> &amp;c. To this it belongs what my Lord <hi>Vaughan</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Reports. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon</hi> and <hi>Burwells</hi> Caſe, <hi>p.</hi> 241. in the <hi>Britiſh</hi> names of Kindred my <hi>Fathers Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin German</hi> hath the Appellation of my <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</hi> and again in the very next Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph. <hi>The word</hi> Uncle <hi>is an equivocal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and in ſeveral places ſignifies ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51688:3"/> 
               <hi>Relations;</hi> as in the <hi>Britiſh,</hi> the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> or <hi>Grandfathers Couſin German</hi> is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> to the <hi>Son.—</hi>But this was for no other reaſon, but becauſe <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin Germans</hi> in antient eſteem were look'd upon as <hi>Brothers,</hi> and unleſs when they expreſs it by a <hi>Periphraſis,</hi> the <hi>Hebrews</hi> have no one word to ſignifie a <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> unleſs you will grant it to be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded under the name of <hi>Brother,</hi> which as it belongs in its utmoſt latitude, to the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and then more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictively to all of the ſame Tribe, the ſame Family or Kindred, ſo next to its moſt narrow and proper acceptation, it belongs moſt peculiarly to a <hi>Couſin German,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when the Declarative Circumſtance is added, of his being <hi>born abroad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 39. The <hi>Jews</hi> interpret this place of two real and proper <hi>Siſters, &amp;c.)</hi> That is, the <hi>Rabbinical Jews,</hi> for the <hi>Karraites</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it as I do, as a prohibition of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygamy,</hi> and in this they are followed by <hi>Franciſcus Junius</hi> and his Fellow-Partner in the Tranſlation of the Bible <hi>Emanuel Tremellius,</hi> a converted <hi>Jew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 42. This was not at firſt deny'd to Clergy-men themſelves) this is thus far true, that being married before hand, did not hinder a Man from entring into Holy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51688:4"/> Orders, but after he was once entered, he could not Marry, though I confeſs, I did not conſider this when I wrote this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, but this is an Obſervation, though natural from the Premiſes, yet foreign to our purpoſe; and it is no matter as to this particular buſineſs, whether it be true or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 48. That Marriage cannot be divorc'd by virtue of any Law—which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſly forbidden in it ſelf, nor ſtands in the ſame rational parity with that which is) This is no more then what my L. C. J. <hi>Vaughan</hi> ſaith in the Caſe already mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>p.</hi> 209. <hi>If Marriages neither prohibited</hi> in terminis <hi>in</hi> Leviticus, <hi>nor being in the ſame Degree with a Marriage there prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhould be unlawful, there would be no ſtop or</hi> terminus <hi>of unlawful Marriages.—</hi>Now I have proved undeniably, That the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> and <hi>Niece</hi> is really a Degree lower, when we ſpeak of Marriage, than the <hi>Aunt</hi> and <hi>Nephew:</hi> And beſides, ſuppoſing the Marriage of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> and <hi>Niece</hi> had been forbidden expreſly, or by juſt and lawful Conſequence, as it is by neither; yet here there would two other Queſtions have ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: Firſt, Whether the Prohibition did equally extend to the <hi>half</hi> Blood as the <hi>whole?</hi> And this St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> tho' other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51688:4"/> a rigid Man in theſe Caſes, ſeems to have doubted very much; at leaſt, he would not abſolutely pronounce the <hi>Half Blood</hi> to be unlawful, in the Caſe of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> Marrying <hi>ſuch</hi> a Niece; but he ſaith of it, <hi>Hic autem gradus tertius eſt, qui etiam jure civili a conſortio conjugii exceptus</hi> videtur; doubting, as it ſeems, within himſelf, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Obligation of that Civil Law, which forbad the Marriage of the <hi>Siſters Daughter,</hi> did extend ſo far as to the <hi>Half Blood</hi> or no, and much more to the Half Blood by the <hi>Father</hi>'s Side, which was the Caſe of <hi>Paternus</hi> his Son. And from hence the ſecond Queſtion ariſes, Whether the Half Blood by the <hi>Father's</hi> Side, be not ſtill a Degree or a Remove further than the Half Blood by the <hi>Mothers?</hi> And this Queſtion, after what I have ſaid concerning it, I leave to the Adverſaries of this Cauſe to determine for themſelves; and if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the Marriage of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> and <hi>Niece</hi> is not forbidden any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by a <hi>Parity</hi> betwixt that and the Marriage of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew;</hi> and if <hi>this</hi> Parity be <hi>no</hi> Parity at all, no more than Even and Odd are <hi>paria</hi> to one another; if beſides this Diſparity, which I have ſhown to be threefold in the firſt Caſe, there be likewiſe a twofold Diſparity
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51688:5"/> ariſing from the Half-Blood, he muſt needs be a very hardy Man, that in the face of <hi>five</hi> good Reaſons againſt his Aſſertion, will ſtill pretend to ſay the Caſe is the <hi>ſame.</hi> At this rate of arguing, any thing may be inferr'd from any thing, and we may ſay very ſafely and aſſuredly with my Lord <hi>Vaughan,</hi> That <hi>there will be no ſtop or</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus <hi>of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Marriages.</hi> And in another place, to aſſure this Point the more effectually, the ſame <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Juſticiary ſaith, <hi>We take the Degrees of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">240. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marriage, prohibited by God's Law, to be the</hi> Levitical <hi>Degrees</hi> expreſſed, <hi>or</hi> neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily implied by <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon, or <hi>a fortiori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 54. The Argument of St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> againſt the Marriage of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> preſſes the hardeſt of any other up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us.) My Anſwer to this Objection of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> to the beſt of my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, would not be unſatisfactory, tho' it had been the Niece by the Whole Blood, as it was not. But this was <hi>Man</hi>'s Caſe in <hi>Crook</hi>'s Reports, who for Marrying his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a p.</hi> 247.</note> 
               <hi>Wives Siſters Daughter,</hi> which is a <hi>Niece</hi> in Affinity, was by the High Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners divorced, upon this Reaſon, becauſe Degrees more remote * were forbidden, <note place="margin">That is, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </note> tho' they confeſſed themſelves at the ſame
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51688:5"/> time, that it was not prohibited within the <hi>Levitical</hi> Degrees; and for that Reaſon, upon the Suit of the Plaintiff, a Prohibition <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ib. p.</hi> 24</note> and Conſultation was granted; but the Iſſue of it cannot be found upon Record.</p>
            <p>After this, in the time of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, for the former Caſe was in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth)</hi> there was ſuch <note place="margin">ib.</note> another Caſe of one <hi>Richard Pearſon,</hi> wherein a Prohibition was granted out of the <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> Court, for Marrying his <hi>Wives Siſters Daughter;</hi> and it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the ſaid Court, upon conſideration of the Statute 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 38. That <hi>the Marriage was not to be impeach'd, becauſe declared by the ſaid Act to be good, in as much as it was not prohibited by the</hi> Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <hi>Degrees.</hi> Which Determination of the Judges of that Court, at that time, muſt of neceſſity proceed upon one of theſe two Suppoſitions; either that our Law had no regard to <hi>Parity</hi> of <hi>Reaſon</hi> in theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; or, that there was indeed <hi>no Parity</hi> betwixt the Marriage of an <hi>Aunt</hi> and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew,</hi> and that of a Man's marrying his <hi>Wives Siſters Daughter,</hi> which is his <hi>Niece</hi> by <hi>Affinity.</hi> But now, ſince <hi>Conſanguini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and <hi>Affinities,</hi> by the <hi>Levitical</hi> as well as <hi>Civil</hi> Law, are the <hi>ſame,</hi> and <hi>equally</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to the <hi>ſame</hi> Degrees, it follows,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51688:6"/> That if in the Judgment of our Law, the Marriage of the <hi>Wives Siſters Daughter</hi> ſhall ſtand good, ſo ſhall that likewiſe which is Conſummated with her who is <hi>Daughter by the Half-Brother on the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Side.</hi> And indeed, the <hi>Half Blood</hi> by the more <hi>uncertain</hi> and <hi>imperfect</hi> Side, makes it ſtill come nigher to <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Pearſon</hi>'s Caſe, and makes it rather an <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine</hi> than <hi>Conſanguineous</hi> Relation.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, in the Caſe of <hi>Harriſon</hi> and <hi>Burwell</hi> it ſelf, <hi>Harriſon</hi> had Married his <hi>Great Aunt,</hi> the Widow of <hi>Abbot</hi> his <hi>Grandfather's Brother;</hi> and my L. <hi>Vaughan</hi> declares this Marriage to be valid, <hi>p.</hi> 207. And this Caſe, by the <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hill.</hi> 21 <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</note> King's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, being referred to the Opinion of all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> 
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Trin.</hi> 22. <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</note> the Chief-Juſtice delivered their Opinions, and accordingly Judgment was given, That <hi>a Prohibition ought to go to the Spiritual Court for the Plaintiff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now there is nothing more clear, than that the <hi>Aunt</hi> is <hi>expreſly</hi> forbidden to the <hi>Nephew</hi> in Marriage; and for this Reaſon, which the Law aſſigns, <hi>She is thine Aunt,</hi> thy <hi>Senior,</hi> thy <hi>Superior,</hi> and, in Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Law, <hi>Parentis loco.</hi> All which do hold as well, tho' not ſo immediately, and indeed the two firſt much more ſtrongly, in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51688:6"/> the <hi>Great Aunt,</hi> than in the <hi>Aunt</hi> at the firſt remove. As the <hi>Jews</hi> in their prohibitory Tables do forbid by Analogy of Reaſon, as they conceive, not only the <hi>Wives Mother,</hi> which is expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. 17. but alſo her <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V. Selden Ux. Hebr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> L.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp; de ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nat. &amp; Gent. L.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> the one being look'd upon <hi>Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis loco</hi> as much as the other, though not ſo immediate as the other is; but the Law of <hi>England</hi> proceeding only by the <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> without any regard, or at leaſt very little to <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon, (for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the <hi>Daughter</hi> and the <hi>Whole Siſter</hi> are not inferr'd to be unlawful by a <hi>Parity,</hi> but by a manifeſt <hi>Superiority</hi> of Reaſon) would not diſanul the Marriage of the <hi>Great Aunt,</hi> though the <hi>immediate</hi> were <hi>ſo expreſly</hi> forbidden.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew yet further, That our Law in <hi>Matrimonial</hi> Caſes do's not proceed by <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon, at leaſt where that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> is ſo <hi>obſcure,</hi> and ſo <hi>many ways</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, as it is in our Caſe; there are two paſſages of the ſame Judge <hi>Vaughan</hi> in his Report of the aforeſaid Caſe of <hi>Harriſon</hi> and <hi>Burwell</hi> which are very well worthy our notice and obſervation; the firſt is, where ſpeaking of the Act 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 38. he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 211. <hi>Thoſe words,</hi> God's Law except, <hi>muſt refer to ſuch other Marriages</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51688:7"/> 
               <hi>as by Gods Law might be impeach'd, and not to any for conſanguinity or affinity, for had not thoſe words been, the generality of expreſſion,</hi> no Marriage ſhall be impeach'd without the <hi>Levitical</hi> degrees, <hi>had exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the impeaching Marriages for plurality of Wives or Husbands at a time, for Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, and for Adultery, as Sir</hi> Edward Coke <hi>obſerves, at the end of his Comment upon this Statute in his ſecond Book of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes.—</hi>Adultery and Polygamy are both of them forbidden by the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law, but when we ſpeak of the <hi>Levitical Degrees</hi> of Affinity and Conſanguinity, they cannot properly be referred to them, and the ſenſe of theſe two <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> Gentlemen is this, that though Adultery, Polygamy, and Impotency are warrantable Cauſes of Divorce according to <hi>Gods Law,</hi> yet if the Act of Parliament had not mentioned <hi>Gods Law,</hi> but only inſiſted upon the <hi>Levitical</hi> degrees, there could no Divorce have enſued, by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> which keeps it ſelf moſt ſtrictly to the Letter, in any of theſe Caſes.</p>
            <p>The other Paſſage which I aim at is this; where ſpeaking of the Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament 25 <hi>&amp;</hi> 28 <hi>H.</hi> 8. concerning the Succeſſion, wherein the <hi>Matrimonial</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51688:7"/> are limited and declared from the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law, he ſaith thus, <hi>p.</hi> 216. <hi>The Marriages particularly declared by the Acts to be againſt God's Law, cannot be diſpens'd with; but other Marriages, not by the Acts declared in particular to be againſt God's Law, are left</hi> ſtatu quo prius, <hi>as to Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations with them:</hi> that is, ſo far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the <hi>Levitical</hi> Degrees, they may be, and are actually diſpenſed with; not by the <hi>Pope,</hi> whoſe Power of Diſpenſation was now aboliſh'd and abrogated for ever; nor by any <hi>Prieſtly Abſolution,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts only for what is paſt, but cannot make any thing lawful <hi>de futuro,</hi> which either the Law of God or Man makes null and void: but by the <hi>Law it ſelf,</hi> which by not prohibiting ſuch Marriages, hath made them Lawful.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, there are other Bars to Matrimony, beſides the <hi>Levitical</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which are included in the Act 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 38. under the general Term of <hi>God's Law,</hi> as hath been already obſerved: But yet my L. C. J. <hi>Coke</hi> was of another <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cok. Lit. F.</hi> 235. <hi>a.</hi>
               </note> mind, he underſtanding <hi>God's Law</hi> and the <hi>Levitical</hi> Degrees, to be only Terms de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative of one another. And in this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation he ſeems to be favoured by the Words of the Act of Parliament, 28 <hi>H.</hi> 8.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51688:8"/> 
               <hi>c.</hi> 16. whereby it is Enacted, That <hi>all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages ſolemnized within this Realm—which be not prohibited by God's Law, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and declared in the Act made this preſent Parliament, for eſtabliſhing the King's Succeſſion, or otherwiſe by Holy Scripture, ſhall be lawful and effectual by Authority of this preſent Parliament.</hi> Where there is no Queſtion but by <hi>God's Law</hi> and the <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Degrees limited, and declared</hi> by that Act of Parliament, as alſo by another be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, in the Twenty fifth of the ſame King, the ſame thing is to be underſtood; but when it is added, <hi>or otherwiſe by Holy Scripture;</hi> it is imply'd by this, that there are other barrs to Matrimony beſides the <hi>Levitical</hi> Degrees: Yet notwithſtanding, when in the Act 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 38. <hi>God's Law</hi> is only mentioned, without the inſertion of that other Clauſe, <hi>or otherwiſe by Holy Scripture,</hi> we muſt either ſay, that the Parliament at that time had not ſo great a deference and regard to Holy Scripture, as when the former Act was made, or elſe, that under the comprehenſive terms of <hi>God's Law,</hi> not only the <hi>Levitical Degrees,</hi> but <hi>all Scripture</hi> in general is included, and this is certainly moſt reaſonable to believe, the Deſign and Intention of all theſe Acts of Parliament being only to reduce the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51688:8"/> Prohibitions, and the cauſes of Divorce to the Standard of God's <hi>Revealed Will,</hi> and to evacuate, annul, and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Encroachments and Uſurpations of the <hi>Canon</hi> Law; ſo that in this I agree perfectly with <hi>Vaughan</hi> againſt <hi>Coke,</hi> but this do's not properly concern our Caſe, for it is the <hi>Levitical Degrees</hi> and they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to which we are to appeal.</p>
            <p>I wiſh my Lord <hi>Vaughan,</hi> as he diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with <hi>Coke</hi> in this particular, in which we are not concerned, ſo in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in which we are, he had not diſagreed with himſelf. For notwithſtanding, in what hath been cited out of him above, he do's ſo plainly intimate, that we are not to ſtrain the <hi>obligation</hi> of theſe Laws be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>Letter</hi> of them; yet, <hi>p.</hi> 216. he ſays, <hi>No degrees being mentioned in the Statute to be prohibited by God's Law, but thoſe which are expreſs'd, it cannot thence be concluded, that the Statute intended no other than thoſe to be prohibited by God's Law, for take the words at moſt advantage for the purpoſe,</hi> viz. Since many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences have fallen by Marrying within the Degrees prohibited by God's Law; that is to ſay, the Son to Marry the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Brother the Siſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the ſame manner is it, if a Statute ſhould ſay,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51688:9"/> 
               <hi>Since many inconveniencies have happened,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">P. 217.</note> 
               <hi>by doing things prohibited by the Kings Laws;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>by depopulation of Farms, by ſubſtracting of Tithes,</hi> &amp;c. It would not be concluded that the things ſo enumerated were all the things prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Kings Laws.</p>
            <p>For, beſides that this ſeems to be a flat Contradiction to what he had ſaid before, That <hi>all Marriages particularly declared by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 216.</note> 
               <hi>the Acts to be againſt God's Law, cannot be diſpenſed with; but that all others may;</hi> or in Words to that effect; the Caſe is not the ſame in theſe two ſeveral Examples: For, when we ſpeak of <hi>Levitical Degrees</hi> prohibited by <hi>God's Law,</hi> and then enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate all the ſeveral Particulars, as they are ſet down in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> than which there are no more Particulars of Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Degrees any where to be found in Scripture, in this Caſe <hi>God's Law,</hi> and the <hi>particular</hi> Branches of it thereafter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, being taken <hi>all together,</hi> are co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extended to one another. But when we ſay, <hi>Whereas many Inconveniencies have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, by doing things prohibited by the King's Laws,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> inſtancing in three or four Particulars only; it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that the <hi>King's Laws</hi> are abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>greater latitude</hi> than the <hi>Particulars</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51688:9"/> that follow. But yet the words, <hi>That is to ſay,</hi> in both Caſes refer only to the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars thereafter expreſſed; and if there be any other things prohibited by the <hi>King's Laws,</hi> which are not expreſſed and enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merated in theſe Particulars, the abſtaining from ſuch forbidden Practices as thoſe, is not bound upon us by vertue of this Law, but by the particular Sanctions of other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Laws, wherein thoſe Offences or Enormities are forbidden: For it would be a ſtrange thing for a Man to be hanged for <hi>ſtealing an Horſe,</hi> by virtue of a Law which puniſhes the <hi>Non-payment of Tythes.</hi> How can thoſe words, <hi>That is to ſay,</hi> be referred to thoſe Particulars which are <hi>no where ſaid</hi> or <hi>expreſſed?</hi> or the words <hi>before-rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> or <hi>above-expreſſed,</hi> to thoſe which are <hi>no where rehearſed,</hi> or <hi>expreſſed?</hi> I do not ſay that a <hi>Parity</hi> or <hi>Superiority</hi> of reaſon is not to be admitted, but I ſay the words of a Statute, which is the Statute-Law, will extend no further than themſelves, and in what inſtances this <hi>Parity</hi> or <hi>Potio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of Reaſon lies, belongs to a Court of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or of <hi>Equity</hi> to determine, but then theſe Inſtances are not referr'd to by the Words, <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> or by the Words <hi>afore-rehearſed</hi> or <hi>above expreſſed,</hi> which belong only to the <hi>naked Letter</hi> of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51688:10"/> Law, but they are pointed at by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances themſelves,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Inſtances</hi> by <hi>Parity</hi> or <hi>Superiority</hi> of Reaſon do point at <hi>other</hi> Inſtances that are not mentioned; as for example, When it is forbidden to Marry the <hi>Half-Siſter,</hi> this evidently darts a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition upon the <hi>Whole-Siſter</hi> likewiſe, becauſe the <hi>Whole-Siſter</hi> is <hi>really</hi> the <hi>Half-Siſter</hi> and <hi>ſomething more;</hi> and when it is forbidden for a Man to Marry his <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child;</hi> this points ſtill more ſtrongly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Daughter:</hi> for, if the <hi>Grandchild</hi> be forbidden for the ſake of the <hi>Daughter,</hi> as there is no queſtion that is the reaſon, the <hi>Daughter</hi> is much more forbidden for her <hi>own</hi> and her <hi>Father's</hi> ſake, and for the ſake of the <hi>Grandchild,</hi> who is for her ſake expreſly forbidden at a further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move: But if where there is neither an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> Prohibition, nor ſo much as a <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon, we will ſuppoſe a Law, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to oblige, which is exactly our Caſe; we may as well extend the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition <hi>in infinitum,</hi> ſo that there need have been but one Prohibition of Marriage, and that would effectually have barred all other Inſtances that can be ſuppoſed, for where a Prohibition ſtops not with <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon, what <hi>other</hi> Limit or Bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry can we ſet?</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51688:10"/>
            <p> Neither let any Man take ſhelter in Archbiſhop <hi>Parker</hi>'s Matrimonial Table, which being firſt publiſh'd in 1563. was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the Year 1603. among many other Canons of a Convocation held that Year, being 1 <hi>Jacobi</hi> 1. ratified, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and allowed under the Broad Seal of <hi>England,</hi> in which <hi>Matrimonial</hi> Table a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other Prohibitions the Marriage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece</hi> is forbidden.</p>
            <p>For this Table was made with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable reguard to the <hi>Levitical</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions, and it was upon ſuppoſition of a <hi>Parity</hi> of reaſon betwixt the Marriage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> and that of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew;</hi> that the former of theſe was prohibited in that Table, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it be not expreſly mention'd in the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> it ſelf, but now ſince I have ſhewn plainly that there is <hi>no</hi> ſuch Parity of Reaſon as is pretended, the Table cannot prohibit ſuch Marriages any longer, unleſs the Act of Parliament muſt give place to the Table: For by the Act of 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 38. it is expreſly ordained, that, <hi>No Reſervation or Prohibition, God's Law except, ſhall trouble or impeach any Marriage without the Levitical Degrees;</hi> and what thoſe Degrees are, appears by 28 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 16. wherein thoſe Degrees are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51688:11"/> ſaid to be <hi>limited</hi> and <hi>declared</hi> in the Act made for eſtabliſhing the Kings Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is, 28 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 7. wherein the Degrees expreſly mentioned and ſet down in <hi>Leviticus</hi> are expreſt, and none other; and if we add any other, but what are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded</hi> in the Degrees mentioned, either by <hi>Parity</hi> or <hi>Potiority</hi> of Reaſon, there can be no end of Prohibitions while the World ſtands, but they may be heap'd and piled <hi>in infinitum</hi> upon one another, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other Authority to make them good, then what either prejudice or fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhall create. I demand therefore, if the Marriage Table had quite altered the Degrees mentioned in <hi>Leviticus</hi> and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted others in their ſtead, whether it would have obliged or no, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Act of Parliament expreſly ſaith, that, <hi>No Reſervation or Prohibition, God's Law except, ſhall trouble or impeach any Marriage without the Levitical Degrees,</hi> which Degrees by another Act are <hi>limited</hi> and <hi>declared,</hi> as aforeſaid? I believe no Man will be found ſo hardy as to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Patronage of this Doctrine, and ſince the reaſon is the ſame in all, there can be no Prohibition in any one Caſe, (and conſequently not in ours nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) where the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> allows a Diſpenſation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51688:11"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>P.</hi> 58. And all ſuch Marriages were pronounced Valid) It is true, this Act of Parliament, ſo far as concerns Precon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts was repealed 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. 23. and that Repeal confirmed 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. but it was for the greater inconveniences which were found by experience by nulling of real Contracts, then by pretending of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, where there were really none, which was the reaſon of the Act in <hi>Henry the Eighth</hi>'s time, and is a plain inſtance in both Caſes, for the Repeal was not founded upon Right but Convenience, that Laws in many Inſtances do not ſo much regard, <hi>Quid fieri jus faſque ſit,</hi> as <hi>Quid expediat, vel interſit Reip. ut fiat, vel non fiat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 72. Being only the half Siſter by the Father's ſide) the Daughter of the <hi>Half-Brother</hi> by the <hi>Father's</hi> ſide, which is a <hi>double</hi> Paternal Conſanguinity, ſo that our Caſe is more favourable than that of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> which made him notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heſitate a little, in ſpite of all his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and Severity in theſe matters; I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no Man will ſay, that the <hi>Half-blood</hi> and the <hi>Whole</hi> are the ſame; and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Caſe with reſpect to <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife, is an unanſwerable inſtance for the <hi>Fathers</hi> ſide, that it is more favourable and more
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51688:12"/> allowable in Marriage than the <hi>Mothers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ib.</hi> Cannot without Ignorance or Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in either Caſe without palpable injuſtice be vacated or diſſolved) This ought not, and, I hope, it will not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted as any diſreſpect to any Court of Juſtice, for I honour the Seats of Juſtice with all my Heart, and will do as much as any Man to the utmoſt of my Power to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert their juſt Authority and Reputation, for as much therefore as I am given to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there is a Sentence paſſed in this Cauſe to the prejudice of the parties in in whoſe behalf I have pleaded, I do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declare, that theſe Papers were written a good while before the paſſing of that Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and that they were actually Printed before it was poſſibly for me to know any thing of it, beſides that a wrong Sentence may ſometimes be pronounced not only by an Upright Judge, but a Wiſe and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one too.—</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51688:12"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> AN ADDITION Of ſome other CONSIDERATIONS Not hitherto ſuggeſted.</head>
            <p>FIrſt, As to the Half-Blood, the <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudical</hi> Doctors were of opinion, that though it were forbidden for a Man to Marry his <hi>Brother's Wife,</hi> in any <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Selden U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hebr. L. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c.</hi> 2.</note> Caſe but only where the Brother died without Iſſue; yet this was to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood only of the Brother by the <hi>ſame</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but that it did not hold in the <hi>Frater <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terinus.</hi> Which Opinion of theirs was founded upon this Reaſon, That the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, which was the Reaſon of ſuch Marriages in default of Iſſue, did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from the Mother, but the Father; ſo that the Law of the <hi>Leviratus</hi> was not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51688:13"/> concerned in the Caſe of a <hi>Frater <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>teri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who was reputed of another and a diſtinct Family from his <hi>Half-Brother</hi> by <hi>another Father,</hi> though the Mother on both Sides were the <hi>ſame.</hi> I confeſs, I am very clear and poſitive againſt the <hi>Rabbins</hi> in this: For whatever becomes of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, it is certain, that in caſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, the Brother by the <hi>Father</hi>'s Side was forbidden upon account of <hi>nearneſs of Kin;</hi> but that <hi>nearneſs,</hi> for the Reaſon already mentioned more than once, is certainly greater in conſtruction of Law on the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>'s Side, than on the <hi>Father</hi>'s. But I bring this Determination of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> whether true or falſe, to ſhew that they did not think the Half-Blood ſo ſacred, and ſo indiſpenſably prohibited as the Whole; and that the Half-Blood on one Side may poſſibly in ſome Inſtances be more ſeverely prohibited than the other: And if this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine will hold in any Caſe, it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in ours, the Father's Side being certainly, as to Legal Conſtruction, the weaker Conſanguinity of the two.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Though my Lord <hi>Vaughan,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill <hi>and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>od<hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe, p.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> in <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Good</hi>'s Caſe, be very inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with himſelf, if we compare him with himſelf in <hi>Harriſon</hi> and <hi>Burwell</hi>'s, where he ſpeaks very favourably of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51688:13"/> Marriage of a Man with his <hi>Wives Siſters Daughter:</hi> for in this latter Caſe of <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> citing all the ſame Precedents he had done before, he concludes, <hi>By all theſe Caſes, the Marriage of the Husband with his Wives Siſters Daughter, is a Marriage prohibited within the Levitical Degrees, for nearneſs of Kindred to the Wife:</hi> Yet afterwards he makes us a ſufficient Amends, if a flat, poſitive, and deliberate Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction can do it. For within a very few Pages afterwards he puts the ſame Caſe, and reſolves it as follows. <hi>A Man before</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ib. p.</hi> 326.</note> 
               <hi>the third of</hi> November, 26 H. 8. <hi>by Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation from</hi> Rome, <hi>had married his Wives Siſters Daughter, which Marriage was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by the Canons of the Church; and no Divorce had been attempted in the Caſe, until after</hi> 1 Eliz. <hi>and the Reviver of the Statute of</hi> 28 H. 8. c. 16. <hi>which made void all Diſpenſations from</hi> Rome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is plain, that this Marriage being not prohibited by God's Law, limited and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the Act of</hi> 28 H. 8. c. 7. <hi>was by the expreſs Words of the revived Act of</hi> 28 H. 8. c. 16. <hi>a Marriage to continue good without Separation, notwithſtanding all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations from</hi> Rome <hi>were null'd; becauſe it was no Marriage excepted out of the Grace intended to be given by that Act to the</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51688:14"/> 
               <hi>King's Subjects Married by Diſpenſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> November <hi>the third,</hi> 26 H. 8. <hi>and not then ſeparated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now from this Determination of my Lord <hi>Vaughan</hi>'s, the Inference is plain, That our Caſe muſt ſtand <hi>a fortiori:</hi> For <hi>Conſanguinities</hi> and <hi>Affinities</hi> in theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are the <hi>ſame,</hi> and prohibited to the <hi>ſame</hi> Degrees; a Man and his Wife are all one; and his <hi>Wives Siſter,</hi> as to this Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, is the ſame with his <hi>own;</hi> and <hi>her Daughter,</hi> the ſame with <hi>his Conſanguine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Niece</hi> by the <hi>Whole</hi> Siſter; which if it be determin'd lawful, the Daughter of the <hi>Half-Brother</hi> is much more, the <hi>Half-Blood</hi> and the <hi>Paternal</hi> Conſanguinity ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together, making the Caſe more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable by <hi>Four</hi> to <hi>One,</hi> which is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Proportion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Though it be true what I have affirmed, That the <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> or <hi>Traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> Doctors are agreed in permitting the Marriage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> and this as far off as the time of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> and probably a great deal longer; yet the <hi>Kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raites</hi> or <hi>Scriptuary Jews</hi> forbid it, as well by the <hi>Brother,</hi> as the <hi>Siſters</hi> Side, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, as I ſuppoſe, to be included by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Reaſon: But this is ſo far from being a Prejudice to our Cauſe, that it is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51688:14"/> the greateſt advantage it can poſſibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, for it is abſurd to think that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Miſnical</hi> or <hi>Traditionary Jews</hi> were ignorant of this Opinion of the <hi>Karraitiſh</hi> Faction, and therefore their determination in this caſe did not proceed out of <hi>heedleſneſs</hi> or <hi>inadvertency,</hi> as it is found to have done in many others, but was certainly grounded upon <hi>one</hi> of theſe <hi>two</hi> bottoms, either that <hi>Parity of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was not to be regarded, and that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Antient Tradition, it did not indiſpenſably oblige their Forefathers, who upon Prudential Conſiderations aſſumed a latitude and liberty to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, either of entring into ſuch Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, or abſtaining from them; or elſe, that there was indeed <hi>no Parity</hi> in this Caſe, as certainly there is not, and much leſs in the <hi>Half-blood,</hi> and the <hi>Half-blood by the Fathers ſide;</hi> and though I am no great friend to the <hi>Traditions</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which in many caſes are monſtruouſly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous and impertinent, yet where a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition hath reaſon to aſſert it, this is a great Argument of its Truth and Credit, and the Reaſon and Tradition do reflect upon each other a mutual Authority and Reputation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly</hi> and <hi>laſtly,</hi> Though Archibiſhop
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51688:15"/> 
               <hi>Parkers</hi> Matrimonial Table were confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Authority of a Convocation in the Second of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt; yet it is to be conſidered, that the power of ſuch Aſſemblies, and Synods of the Clergy, and the Validity of what they ſhall determine is founded upon 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. and in that Act there is this proviſion made; <hi>Provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alway, that no Canons, Conſtitutions or Ordinances ſhall be made or put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on within this Realm, by Authority of the Convocation of the Clergy, which ſhall be contrariant or repugnant to the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Royal, or the Cuſtoms, Laws or Statutes of this Realm.</hi> Wherefore all the Queſtion is, whether this Marriage be againſt the <hi>Law of God,</hi> as I think I have abundantly proved that it is not, and upon ſuppoſition that I am in the right, the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial</hi> Table, as to this particular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition is of no manner of force or obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe the Statute of 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 38. expreſly ſays, That <hi>no Reſervation or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, Gods Law except, ſhall trouble or impeach any Marriage.</hi> And this is all I have to ſay, only ſince there is a Sentence of Divorce already paſt in this Cauſe, I would humbly recommend it to thoſe before whom the final determination of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie ſhall lie, that they would reflect
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51688:15"/> upon our <hi>Saviours</hi> injunction in Caſes of this Nature, <hi>whom God hath joyn'd,</hi> (as he hath joyned all thoſe who being actually Married, are not antecedently by his Law forbidden to Marry) <hi>let no man put aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and that in the Judgment they ſhall give upon this Caſe, they would ſet the great Judge of Heaven and Earth before them as a Pattern, who hath told us not only for our inſtruction, but imitation too. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I will have Mercy and not Sacrifice, and that in the midſt of Judgment he remembers Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51688:16"/>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51688:16"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Reliquiae Secundae.</head>
            <p>I Did believe upon the Writing of my laſt Paper that I had exhauſted the Argument which was the Subject of it, but upon further enquiry I find I have not, and there is further to be added, to what I have ſaid already, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Learned Men are divided in their Opinions, whether the Prohibitions in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticus</hi> are <hi>Natural,</hi> that is, founded and rooted in the Law of Nature, or in the Natural and Eternal Reaſon of things, or whether they are purely <hi>poſitive</hi> and no more. Of the <hi>firſt</hi> ſort is <hi>Lyranus, Abulenſis, Bonfrerius, Maſius, Montanus,</hi> and <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Serarius,</hi> and among the Reformed Mr. <hi>Calvin;</hi> of the <hi>latter</hi> is <hi>Paulus Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſis, Cajetanus, C. a Lapide, Sanchez,</hi> and the Authors by him cited, <hi>Tirinus, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus, Menochius,</hi> and <hi>Magalianus,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Reformed three great Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Druſius, Epiſcopius,</hi> and our Learned
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51688:17"/> Biſhop <hi>Taylor;</hi> as for mine own Opinion, I muſt confeſs, that I incline rather to the Sentiments of the <hi>former,</hi> but they that think with the <hi>latter,</hi> that the Obligation of theſe Laws is <hi>poſitive and no more,</hi> they have no pretence for a Diſſolution of this Marriage, becauſe in Laws <hi>meerly poſitive</hi> there is no ſuch thing as <hi>Parity</hi> to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, ſuch Laws being all of them a manifeſt reſtraint upon the Natural Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Mankind, and therefore ought not to be ſtrained by Parities, and Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whether true or falſe, beyond the Letter of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to my Interpretation of the Phraſe of <hi>Dying Childleſs,</hi> it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Authority of the Learned Jeſuite <hi>Stephanus Menochius,</hi> who in his Comment upon that place, hath theſe remarkable Words to the very ſame Senſe with mine, <hi>Hi inceſtuoſi non ſinentur in hoc ſcelere permanere donec liberos habere poſſint, ſed occidantur,</hi> and this, when all is done, is the true meaning of the Text, though the <hi>Jews</hi> who are horribly unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the remote Antiquities of their own Nation have deviſed other fanciful Gloſſes which will not abide the teſt of a judicious enquiry, and that we may not wonder at this ſeverity of puniſhing all Inceſtuous
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51688:17"/> Conjunctions with Death, <hi>Paulutius Foro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>julienſis</hi> refers it as he very well might, beſides the Reaſon I have given, to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary diſpoſal of Almighty God, who may annex what Sanction he pleaſes to his Laws, or, which is all one, to ſome Impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Cauſe or Motive which he hath not thought fit to reveal, ſo that with reſpect to us it is Arbitrary, let it be what it will in it ſelf, where ſpeaking of Congreſs with a Menſtruous Woman being puniſhed with Death, he ſays, <hi>Multa alia quae non ſunt peccata mortalia puniebantur paenâ mortis ex aliquâ causâ legiſlatorem movente, ut eſus Sanguinis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> When it is ſaid, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. 6. <hi>None of you ſhall approach to any that is near of kin to him, to uncover their Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> It is to be obſerved, that this <hi>near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of kin</hi> is to be meaſured not from <hi>our ſelves,</hi> but from the <hi>Fountain</hi> of Kindred, that is, from a <hi>common</hi> Father or Parent, as when it is ſaid in the Prohibition of the <hi>Aunt</hi> by the <hi>Fathers</hi> ſide, <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>Thou ſhalt not uncover the nakedneſs of thy Fathers Siſter, ſhe is thy Fathers near Kinſwoman.</hi> And again, <hi>v.</hi> 13. of the <hi>Aunt</hi> by the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> ſide, <hi>Thou ſhalt not uncover the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy Mothers Siſter, for ſhe is thy Mothers near Kinſwoman.</hi> It is plain, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51688:18"/> though the <hi>Niece</hi> be at the <hi>ſame</hi> diſtance from me in the <hi>deſcending</hi> Line, that the <hi>Aunt</hi> is in the <hi>aſcending,</hi> yet when the <hi>expreſs</hi> Reaſon aſſigned in the Law, why I may not marry mine <hi>Aunt,</hi> is not becauſe ſhe is <hi>mine,</hi> but my <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mothers near Kinſwoman,</hi> this is ſo far from darting any Prohibition upon my <hi>Niece,</hi> that it is on the contrary, plainly favourable and propitious to a Marriage in that Relation; becauſe my <hi>Niece,</hi> who is my Fathers <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child,</hi> is plainly at a further diſtance from him than mine <hi>Aunt</hi> who is his <hi>Siſter;</hi> and that for two Reaſons, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe the one is an <hi>immediate</hi> Relation, but the other, by the interpoſition of a Son or Daughter betwixt, is a Relation at the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond remove;</hi> and becauſe no Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man can get or bear Children by <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> without the Conjunction of another, it is therefore only a Relation by the <hi>half Blood,</hi> and if it be the <hi>Niece</hi> by the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there is not only the <hi>Half Blood</hi> to be conſidered, but that that <hi>Half Blood it ſelf</hi> is the more <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>uncertain</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity of the two, as hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready frequently declared; ſo that if the <hi>nearneſs</hi> to my <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mother</hi> be the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> Reaſon aſſigned in the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> why I may not Marry mine <hi>Aunt,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51688:18"/> no Man can with any ſhew of Reaſon infer from thence, that I am forbid likewiſe to Marry my <hi>Niece,</hi> becauſe the diſtance is manifeſtly greater from the <hi>Fountain</hi> of Kindred, and the Relation unqueſtionably <hi>more imperfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo, when it is ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>Thou ſhalt not uncover the Nakedneſs of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Brother, thou ſhalt not approach to his Wife, ſhe is thine Aunt.</hi> Here there are three things manifeſtly imply'd, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That in the <hi>Levitical</hi> Prohibitions, <hi>Conſanguinities</hi> and <hi>Affinities</hi> are conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as the <hi>ſame,</hi> and are prohibited to the <hi>ſame</hi> Degrees. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Reaſon of her being forbidden in Marriage is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is my <hi>Brothers Wife,</hi> that is, in Conſtruction of Law, my <hi>Fathers Siſter</hi> or <hi>near Kinſwoman;</hi> And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As in the two former Caſes, that this is done out of reſpect and honour to my Father, with whom ſhe ſtands upon the ſame <hi>Level</hi> or <hi>Horizontal Plane</hi> in the <hi>Scheme</hi> of <hi>Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity</hi> or <hi>Affinity,</hi> ſo that to Marry mine <hi>Aunt</hi> is to make my <hi>Fathers equal</hi> my <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour,</hi> and to ſubject her to the mean and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile condition of a Wife to whom I owe the Service and Honour of a <hi>Parent.</hi> And this is the true Interpretation of thoſe Words in this laſt place, <hi>She is thine Aunt;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51688:19"/> for every Man knows without the help of <hi>Revelation,</hi> that his Fathers Brothers Wife is his <hi>Aunt;</hi> but there is manifeſtly inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in them an intimation of her <hi>Superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> over us, by reaſon of her ſtanding <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual</hi> in the Table of Affinity with our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Mother, and therefore ſhe ought not to ſubmit to have her Nakedneſs unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by her <hi>inferiour</hi> and <hi>dependant,</hi> or put her ſelf into a condition of <hi>Subjection</hi> to him, from whom ſhe may expect and challenge the Duty, Service and Allegiance of a <hi>Son;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Greeks</hi> called the Uncle and Aunt by the names of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, alluding, as I ſuppoſe, in the uſe of theſe words to the Antient, Abſolute and Arbitrary Power which all Parents had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Children; ſo that as to all the inſtances to which their Power or Poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Action could extend it ſelf, they were as abſolute and unaccountable as God himſelf, and were his Vicegerents up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth in their reſpective Families, and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> and <hi>Aunt</hi> were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they had, as it were <hi>Aliquid divini juris in liberos liberaſque fratrum &amp; ſororum,</hi> they had a right of Reverence, and a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural claim of Duty and Reſpect from their Nephews and Nieces, which were accounted but a remove from Children;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51688:19"/> and laid ſo great a weight upon all their Advices, Admonitions and Commands, that to diſobey them in any thing not very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, was accounted an heinous Crime, although their Power of <hi>Coercion</hi> were not all out ſo great, as that of their natural and proper Parents.</p>
            <p>And now from what hath been juſt now ſaid, it is plain, that the Reaſon of that Law by which the <hi>Nephew</hi> is prohibited to Marry his <hi>Aunt,</hi> being founded in theſe two things, <hi>Firſt,</hi> In <hi>nearneſs of Kin,</hi> which is greater to the <hi>Father</hi> in his <hi>Siſter</hi> than his <hi>Grandchild. Secondly,</hi> In the <hi>ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority</hi> and <hi>preeminence</hi> of the <hi>Aunt</hi> over the <hi>Nephew,</hi> I ſay, it is plain that it cannot from <hi>either</hi> of theſe conſiderations be inferred by any <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon, that the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece</hi> is forbidden, and with reſpect to the latter conſideration, the <hi>ſuperiority</hi> is not violated by ſuch a Marriage, but rather pleaſed and gratified by it, becauſe it ſtill continues where it was, that is in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</hi> only by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage it is rendred <hi>more</hi> abſolute and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo that unleſs <hi>contraries</hi> may by <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of Reaſon be inferr'd from <hi>contraies,</hi> there can be no inference from the Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of an <hi>Aunt,</hi> which ſhall debar or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Marriage of a <hi>Niece.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51688:20"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is certain, that <hi>Amram</hi> took to Wife <hi>Jochebed</hi> his <hi>Fathers Siſter,</hi> and this could not be long before the giving of the <hi>Law,</hi> for of that Match <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> were deſcended; the thing is mentioned in more places than one of the Scripture without any manner of blame or reprehenſion, and we are not raſhly to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Perſons that were ſo highly honoured by God with a <hi>Prophetick</hi> Spirit, a gift of <hi>Miracles,</hi> a <hi>Prieſtly Character</hi> annexed for ever to the <hi>Family</hi> of the one, and a <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Power</hi> inveſted by God himſelf in the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the other, to have been Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious or Illegitimate; from whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that whatever reaſons of <hi>Convenience</hi> or <hi>Intereſt</hi> there may be to hinder ſuch Marriages From being entred into, yet it was not a matter of <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable</hi> Obligation till after the giving of the Law by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that if it had not been for the giving of <hi>that Law,</hi> it would have remained ſtill in the ſame prudential indifference which it had before; for what is <hi>once</hi> lawful, muſt <hi>always</hi> continue ſo, till a ſupervening Law forbids it, and makes it unlawful; but if the Marriage of the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew</hi> to his <hi>Aunt</hi> were a Marriage good and valid before the giving of the Law by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> to his <hi>Niece</hi> was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51688:20"/> much more, it being ſhewn in ſo many and various reſpects to be ſo plainly a more favourable Caſe, and therefore not being any where <hi>expreſly</hi> forbidden, it muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill as it was, <hi>prudential</hi> and <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> and conſequently <hi>lawful.</hi> For when reſtraints are lay'd upon <hi>lawful</hi> things, there is no inference from the prohibition of one thing to the prohibition of another by <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon, whether pretended or real, but the Prohibition ſtops within it ſelf, and extends no further than the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as if part of a <hi>Common Field</hi> ſhould be <hi>enclos'd,</hi> and this <hi>Encloſure</hi> eſtabliſh'd and warranted by <hi>Law,</hi> there lies here no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference by <hi>Parity</hi> of Reaſon for the Enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the <hi>reſt,</hi> but what is not <hi>actually</hi> and <hi>legally</hi> enclos'd, is <hi>common,</hi> and muſt remain <hi>open</hi> as it did before.</p>
            <p>Beſides, that <hi>Moſes</hi> by Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould ſo ſeverely forbid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew,</hi> a ſort of Marriage of which he himſelf and his Brother <hi>Aaron</hi> were deſcended, bringing by that means a ſort of <hi>Aſperſion,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is, at leaſt, very like a <hi>Reproach</hi> upon himſelf and his Family, upon his Brother <hi>Aaron</hi> and the Family of <hi>Prieſts</hi> that were for <hi>ever after</hi> deſcended from his Loyns, and yet take no notice in the leaſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51688:21"/> of the Marriage of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> in which he was not concern'd, but might have forbidden it without any manner of reflection upon himſelf or his Relations, if God had intended to prohibit them both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, is a thing to me ſo incredible, that nothing can be more, and I preſume it will appear ſo to every indifferent Perſon that ſhall reflect upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> There is alſo the Caſe of <hi>Achſah</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> in the Books of <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi> in which, if we underſtand the Text ſo as that <hi>Othniel,</hi> who was the Son of <hi>Kenaz,</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Half Brother</hi> of <hi>Caleb</hi> by the <hi>Mothers</hi> ſide, for <hi>Caleb</hi> was not the Son of <hi>Kenaz</hi> but <hi>Jephunneth;</hi> then here is another Inſtance <hi>after</hi> the Law, of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> Marrying his <hi>Niece,</hi> the Daughter of his <hi>Half Brother</hi> by the <hi>Mothers</hi> ſide; the Words of the Text are theſe, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 15. 17. Othniel <hi>the Son of</hi> Kenaz, <hi>the Brother of</hi> Caleb <hi>took it:</hi> (Kirjath-ſepher) <hi>and he gave him</hi> Achſah <hi>his Daughter to Wife.</hi> And again, <hi>Judg.</hi> 1. 13. Othniel <hi>the Son of</hi> Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naz <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See alſo g.</hi> 3. 9.</note> Calebs <hi>younger Brother took it,</hi> (Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jath-ſepher) which words in both places may either be ſo Interpreted, that <hi>Othniel</hi> had this double Relation, he was the Son of <hi>Kenaz,</hi> and he was likewiſe <hi>Calebs</hi> younger Brother by the <hi>Mother</hi>'s ſide, and
<pb facs="tcp:51688:21"/> then <hi>Achſah</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Caleb</hi> will be <hi>Othniel</hi>'s Niece, and his Niece by a <hi>nearer</hi> Conſanguinity than that in the Caſe before us; or elſe, that <hi>Othniel</hi> was the Son of <hi>Kenaz,</hi> which <hi>Kenaz</hi> was younger Brother to <hi>Caleb;</hi> and ſo <hi>Othniel</hi> and <hi>Achſah</hi> will be <hi>Couſin Germans.</hi> Both of theſe Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if there were nothing elſe but theſe Words to be conſidered, are very natural and eaſie; but when I conſider that after the Death of <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were made Captive by <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan-riſhathaim,</hi> for the ſpace of Eight Years, <hi>Judg.</hi> 3. 8. that God raiſed up this <hi>Othniel</hi> to be their Saviour and Deliverer out of the Hands of this Oppreſſor, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. and that <hi>the Land had reſt</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards under the Government of this <hi>Othniel for the ſpace of forty Years;</hi> no Man will ever think that <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> in that Age of the World could probably be the Sons of the ſame Mother, when it is ſo plainly demonſtrable, that there was at leaſt <hi>Forty nine</hi> or <hi>Fifty Years</hi> differance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their Ages, for to this <hi>Fourty eight</hi> we muſt add <hi>one</hi> or <hi>two</hi> more, becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this period began they were both Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary, and <hi>Caleb,</hi> if he were Brother to <hi>Othniel,</hi> was then the elder by a Year or two at the leaſt.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51688:22"/>
            <p> But this is not all, <hi>c.</hi> 2. 8. we have an account that <hi>Joſhua</hi> dy'd, and <hi>v.</hi> 10. That <hi>all that Generation,</hi> of which <hi>Caleb</hi> was one, <hi>were gathered to their Fathers,</hi> and then, before this Revolution of <hi>Cuſhan-riſhatha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im,</hi> we have an account of ſeveral other Oppreſſions which the <hi>Jews</hi> for their many Sins and Provocations laboured under; ſo that the diſtance between the Age of <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> is ſtill conſiderably greater than what hath been repreſented. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains therefore, that <hi>Achſah</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> were <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> that is, <hi>Brothers Children,</hi> who in their Circumſtance might lawfully Marry, for it appears, that <hi>Achſah</hi> was an <hi>Heireſs,</hi> otherwiſe her Father could not have given her the <hi>Southland,</hi> as he did, and added afterwards to it <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper and the Nether Springs,</hi> all which, by the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaick</hi> Platform of Inheritance would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have devolved upon the <hi>Male Iſſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ask how any Woman can be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an <hi>Heireſs</hi> while her Father is yet <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving?</hi> I anſwer, That in ſtrictneſs ſhe could not yet be called by that name, there being <hi>no</hi> Inheritance neceſſarily devolved upon her, but her Father was now ſo old, that he was paſt the hope or expectation of any more Children: For at the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51688:22"/> 
               <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> he was one of the <hi>Heads</hi> of the Tribes, <hi>Numb.</hi> 13. 6. and one of thoſe who together with <hi>Joſhua</hi> and others, <hi>v.</hi> 17. were ſent by <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpy out the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> after this they remained in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> Fourty Years, and <hi>Joſhua</hi> who ſeems to have been much of the ſame Age with <hi>Caleb,</hi> ſoon after his entrance upon the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> dy'd, being at his Death of the Age of <hi>an Hundred and ten Years, Joſh.</hi> 24. 29. <hi>Judg.</hi> 2. 8. And if we allow <hi>ten</hi> or <hi>twenty</hi> Years by which <hi>Joſhua,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reaſon that appears, ſhall be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be older than <hi>Caleb;</hi> the Age of <hi>Caleb</hi> at the Marriage of his Daughter <hi>Achſah,</hi> will be an Hundred or Ninety at the leaſt, wherefore being ſo old and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in Perſon to be at the Head of a Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Aſſault, he propounds the taking of <hi>Kirjath-ſepher</hi> to ſome other with a reward, <hi>He that ſmiteth</hi> Kirjath-ſepher <hi>and taketh it,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to him will I give</hi> Achſah <hi>my Daughter to Wife;</hi> not that any <hi>one</hi> Man could take a City or Town by himſelf, or that every Man was fit to Command a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; or that the <hi>Inheritance</hi> which was to go along with <hi>Achſah,</hi> could be legally diverted from <hi>Othniel,</hi> who was the next <hi>Heir Male</hi> of that Family, only by theſe general words he propounds the Conduct of the Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51688:23"/> to <hi>Othniel</hi> with Promiſe upon Succeſs, that he ſhould immediately be Married to his Daughter, which the Old Man during his Life time, was not obliged to permit, and have part of the Inheritance in hand before hand. And this is the true State of this Caſe, which though in it ſelf it be nothing to our purpoſe, yet there is an uſe that may be made of it, and that is this;</p>
            <p>That it would be very ſtrange, if God had intended equally to prohit the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> as of an <hi>Aunt</hi> with her <hi>Nephew,</hi> not only that he ſhould no where expreſly prohibit the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe, as he hath done the latter, but that the Holy Spirit in this particular Caſe of <hi>Achſah</hi> and <hi>Othniel</hi> ſhould ſpeak of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> after ſuch a manner, that many, and thoſe very Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men too, have been induc'd to believe it was the Marriage of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> with his <hi>Niece,</hi> for of this Opinion were moſt of thoſe whom I have already cited as Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>meerly poſitive</hi> Obligation of the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> and laſtly, Though I am far from diſputing the Kings Power in diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with a Statute in Caſes of neceſſity, of which he is the Judge, yet in ordinary Caſes he is never ſuppoſed to intend it, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51688:23"/> it is certain, that when among other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles preſented to him by the Convocation he gave his Royal Aſſent to the Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Table, in which the Uncle is prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to Marry his <hi>Niece,</hi> the Convocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves were of Opinion, that this Degree was ſome way or other prohibited by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the King agreed to this Prohibition among others, upon that ſuppoſition, but now ſince it appears ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that this ſort of Marriage was never actually forbidden by the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> nor ſo much as intended to be forbidden, either nothing but Gods Law can impeach any Marriage, and by conſequence this cannot be impeach'd, or elſe an Act of Parliament may be Repealed by an Act of Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which yet hath no Power to make any Laws or Ordinances whatſoever, but what the Parliament it ſelf hath given it, and the Parliament can never be ſuppoſed to put a Power deſtructive of their very Conſtitution into the Hands of the Clergy met together in a Convocation; nay, they have expreſly provided, with the Kings Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Aſſent, who, without neceſſity, which cannot here be pretended, will never break his Word with his People, and then the breach of it is the trueſt Juſtice, that no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation ſhall exerciſe any ſuch Power.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51688:24"/>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51688:24"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Additional Advertiſement</hi> Concerning the HALF-BLOOD.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>DEut.</hi> 13. 6. It is provided in caſe of Idolatry; <hi>If thy Brother, the Son of thy Mother, or thy Son, or thy Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or the Wife of thy Boſom, or thy Friend which is as thine own Soul, entice thee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, ſaying, Let us go and ſerve other Gods,</hi> &amp;c. v. 8. <hi>Thou ſhalt not conſent unto him, nor hearken unto him, neither ſhall thine Eye pity him, neither ſhalt thou ſpare, neither ſhalt thou conceal him;</hi> v. 9. <hi>But thou ſhalt ſurely kill him; thine Hand ſhall be firſt upon him to put him to death, and afterwards the Hand of all the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The meaning of this Law is, that Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry ſhould certainly be puniſhed with Death, let the Relation be never ſo nigh, or the Endearment and Friendſhip never ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51688:25"/> great, as appears by thoſe Words, <hi>Or the Wife of thy Boſom, or thy Friend which is as thine own Soul;</hi> and when it is ſaid, <hi>Thy Brother the Son of thy Mother,</hi> without mention of the <hi>Brother by the Father,</hi> it is imply'd, that the one is nearer of kin than the other, in the Interpretation of the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law, this beſt anſwering the intention of this Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> which did oblige them not to conceal even their neareſt Relations, and in this Prohibition the Brother being the Son or ſuppoſed Son of the Father is included <hi>a fortiori.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51688:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books written by the ſame Author, and Printed for</hi> Walter Kettilby, <hi>at the</hi> Biſhops-Head <hi>in St.</hi> Pauls Church-yard.</head>
            <p n="1">1. ANimadverſions upon the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached before the Lord Mayor, <hi>October 19th.</hi> 1679.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Diſcourſe of the Divine Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and its Conſequences, in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached before the Honourable Society of <hi>Lincolns-Inn</hi> the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> of <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term, 1683.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Sermon Preached before Sir <hi>P. W.</hi> 1681. with Additions. To which are annexed three Digreſſional Exercitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I. Concerning the true time of our Saviours Paſſover. II. Concerning the Prohibition of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Canon to the Ancient <hi>Jews.</hi> III. Concerning the <hi>Jewiſh Tetragrammaton,</hi> and the <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorick Tetractys. Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Two Diſcourſes Introductory to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, demonſtrating the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> from Law, Reaſon, Scripture and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:51688:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> 5. A Letter of Reſolution to a Friend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. A Reſolution of Three Matrimonial Caſes, <hi>viz.</hi> I. Whether it be lawful for a Man to Marry his diſceas'd Wives Siſters Daughter. II. Whether the Half-Blood makes Kindred. III. Whether ſuch a Marriage being made, it ought to be diſſolv'd or no.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Boaz</hi> and <hi>Ruth,</hi> A Diſquiſition upon <hi>Deut.</hi> 25. 5. concerning the the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Propagating the Memory of his Elder-Brother deceas'd; in which the Antiquity, Reaſon and Circumſtances of the Law are Explain'd, the Miſtakes and Impoſitions of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rabbins in this and other matters detected, and a fair way opened for a clearer under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the moſt obſcure and dark places in the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> together with a diſcovery of ſeveral things as well in the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> as <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities, never yet explained or underſtood by any.</p>
            <p n="8">8. An Argument in defence of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of an Uncle with the Daughter of his <hi>Half Brother</hi> by the Fathers ſide. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
